Okay so Daf 42 and we pick up at the top first
line and the issue that we're dealing with is the statement that
we're dealing once again with guess what חזקה Chazakah of three years
and the issue we're dealing with is that if one person has
to have that חזקה Chazakah for a continuous period of time because
it's one person being on the land for three years that sort
of demonstrates, you know, makes a statement of their ownership and control
and is seen as sufficient provocation for the original owners to say
something. If it's three different people it wouldn't be a חזקה. Chazakah.
Each one of them would only have a חזקה Chazakah of a
year. But says the גמרא, Gemara, says רב, Rav, that if three
of them are connected because ראובן Reuven was there for a year,
sold it to שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon sold it to לוי, Levi,
then it's all one continuous process because it's all basically asserting ראובן's
Reuven original ownership, then it is a חזקה. Chazakah. But only in
a context where that relationship is known to the original owner, otherwise
from his perspective it's three random people. And therefore it's only if
ראובן Reuven sold it to שמעון Shimon with a שטר Shtar and
שמעון Shimon to לוי Levi with a שטר. Shtar. So שמעון Shimon
and לוי Levi have to be able to produce their שטרות Shtarot
and then ראובן Reuven after three years says hey I didn't hear
you say anything after three years and you should have known what
was going on here because we have all these שטרות Shtarot so
those שטרות Shtarot have to be in evidence, שמעון Shimon and לוי's
Levi שטר, Shtar, but then I stop being careful with my שטר
Shtar because you know you should have known about this and you
didn't respond. Okay so that was the statement of רב Rav and
now the גמרא Gemara is actually challenging is why רב Rav demands
that there be a שטר, Shtar, why is witnesses to the sale
from ראובן Reuven to שמעון Shimon and שמעון Shimon to לוי Levi
not considered sufficient?
You know shouldn't he get the message the original owner even through
witnesses? Don't
witnesses themselves sort of cause the call, cause people to talk about
it and cause the matter to be known, מפיק קלא? mafik kala?
And the גמרא Gemara says no only a שטר Shtar does, not
witnesses. And even though maybe sometimes if something is witnessed that means
if you're purchasing land and as long as it was witnessed you
should be able to find out if there are liens on the
land that's because when you're in the process of buying, buyer beware,
what's that phrase for buyer beware? Caveat emptor. Caveat emptor.
You
know if you're buying and you're about to spend money you need
to do your due diligence and investigate. So as long as there
is evidence even if it's not well known. But if you're the
original owner then prima facie you're seeing three different people that's not
that's not sufficient provocation for you to respond. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara continues with that top line of מ"ב ע"א. Mem Bet
Amud Aleph. ומי אמר רב הכי? Umi amar Rav hachi? Now did
רב Rav really say this?
Did he really say
that when you sell land only with עדים Edim the לוקח Lokei'ach
the purchaser should be able has due diligence and should be able
to investigate and find out that there are liens
that
were created even merely through the presence of עדים Edim even without
a שטר? Shtar? If those liens were created it's the purchaser's obligation
to find them out even if they were only created through the
presence of witnesses. Does he really say this? ותנן Ve-t'nan we taught
in the משנה: Mishnah: המלווה חברו בשטר, Ha-malveh chaveiro bish'tar, גובה מנכסים
משועבדים. Goveh min'chasim meshubadim. If you go ahead
and
I lend Michael money here you see Michael you're always sitting here
you're always the stand-in I lend Michael money with a שטר. Shtar.
Okay so there we wrote a document that says Michael owes me
a thousand dollars. Now if Michael sells his land to Eli over
there I can go ahead and seize it from Eli if Michael
doesn't have funds in his own under his own control. Right, first
I have to try to collect from Michael but if not I
can buy use my liens and collect land that Michael has sold
that he that he sold after the loan. And Eli can't say
hey it's not fair to me because we say no there was
a שטר Shtar and you should have known that there were liens.
So if there's a שטר Shtar then I'm able to use those
liens. Okay but על ידי עדים al yedei edim if I only
lent Michael money with witnesses גובה מנכסים בני חורין. goveh min'chasim bnei
chorin. I can only collect from money that are like unencumbered property,
money under Michael's control, and I can't collect from property with liens
that are under third parties because then Eli will say it's not
fair I had no idea that there were liens on it. You
lent Michael money with witnesses that was not a public matter. So
here you see it's exactly that difference that we've always assumed that
things are known with a שטר, Shtar, they're not known with עדים
Edim which is consistent with רב's Rav original assertion
about חזקה Chazakah done through three people it only works with a
שטר Shtar not with עדים, Edim, only a שטר Shtar makes it
public. But the question is how is this different than the other
teaching of רב Rav that if I sell if I sell Michael
land and the land has אחריות Achrayut on it which means that
there's going to be liens or whatever that Michael can collect from
if the land is seized etc. that that is only if is
even if I sell it to him just with witnesses, even without
a שטר Shtar those types of liens are created. So why when
you sell land with with liability does does that liability exist even
if there's just witnesses, whereas if you lend money, it has to
be lent with a שטר. shtar. What is the story for that
poor guy Eli who's going to buy land? How come when it's
when it's a lien created through a loan is is is the
lien only exist with a שטר, shtar, cause otherwise we say he
can't know about it? But if it's the lien created through insurance
on a sale, then we say that actually it's even through עדים.
eidim. What's the difference? So let's see the גמרא's Gemara answer. So
the
גמרא Gemara says, וכי תימא רב תנא הוא ופליג. vechi teima Rav
tanna hu upalig. Now let's say you say Rav would reject this
statement, and he would say even by a loan, as as as
long even if it's created with witnesses, then Eli should be able
to find that out, and he has to find out that there
are liens, even liens created with witnesses, not not with a שטר.
shtar. You can't say that. ופליג והא רב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו, upalig
veha Rav uShmuel de'amri tarvaihu, because Rav himself together with Shmuel says,
מלוה על פה אינה גובה לא מן היורשים ולא מן הלקוחות. milveh
al peh einah goveh lo min hayorshim velo min halakochot. So if
there was a loan done that was just oral, you can't collect
from a לקוח, lakoach, from a somebody who bought the land from
Michael because that's a purchaser. That's of course what we've been saying
all along, a a somebody who buys land can only the those
liens are only good if if if they were created through a
שטר. shtar. But not only that, even if I lent money to
Reuven and Reuven died, okay, I, forget Eli, I can't collect my
loan from Reuven's heirs without a שטר, shtar, okay, if it's only
through עדים. eidim. I can can only collect it with a שטר,
shtar, only then do I have liens. Otherwise the orphans say, hey,
it was our father who owes money, we don't owe the money,
and you say, well, okay, but you know, we inherited our father's
estate. Well, that's like somebody bought the you know the father's estate,
and therefore your liens on our father's property don't exist because you
don't have a שטר. shtar. Now that is actually not the הלכה.
halacha. The need for a שטר shtar to protect a third party,
right, an innocent third party, right, Michael is going to I mean
Eli is going to go spend money or whatever, we have to
protect him, we say that my liens will exist only if there's
a שטר shtar and he can know about it, he's protected. Okay,
but for the for the orphans, right, they're not spending money, they're
not buying anything, they're just passively inheriting their father's estate, and I
have money owed to me. So why as long you know as
I can prove it I have witnesses, why should I not be
able to collect my liens you know from the father's estate, right?
Do you understand the difference between orphans and the I mean I
know we hear orphans we feel compassionate, okay, somebody could be a
70 year old orphan, right? Okay, what exactly? So anyway, but but
the point you understand the difference, right? Some third party is going
to come and buy something, it's not fair for him if that
land gets seized because of a lien unless he was able to
know about it. But for the people who inherited the father's estate,
it's the opposite. Why should the person who lent money to the
father lose out just because the father died and the land passed
on to the kids? Okay, but anyway but Rav and Shmuel say
no, we have to make it equal. If you don't have liens
vis-a-vis a a
purchaser, you don't have liens vis-a-vis the orphans. That's the חידוש chiddush
of Rav and Shmuel.
If
you don't have liens, if I the guy who lent money don't
have liens against a purchaser because it wasn't done through a שטר
shtar and it wasn't a public matter, so we're not going to
allow me to have those liens against a purchaser, then I won't
have liens even if against the orphans. If the father died, even
though the money was I lent the money and I have witnesses
that can prove it, if it's not if if those if I
don't have liens that could be used against a purchaser because we
protect the purchaser and we need there to be a שטר shtar
and we need there to be a public matter, right, a שטר
shtar you know a documentation, then I won't be able to use
to have liens against the orphans either. That's the חידוש chiddush of
Rav and Shmuel, which we don't פסקן pasken like. We we that's
not the פסק, psak, but I want to say that's their חידוש.
chiddush. Yeah, and everyone knows the הלכה halacha that, meaning that was
the משנה, Mishna, that in order for me to have liens against
a purchaser I need a שטר. shtar. You didn't need Rav and
Shmuel to tell you that. What Rav and Shmuel are telling you
is the same הלכה halacha applies to the orphans. What's relevant for
us is that we see that Rav himself agrees to this distinction
that we all know between a שטר shtar and witnesses. So why
doesn't he hold of that distinction when it comes to liens created
through insurance of a sale? Why does he hold of the distinction
when it comes to liens created through a loan, but not through
liens created through insurance of a sale? Yes, Rabbi Dov, and then
I'll get back to you.
Question about the heir is whether you see the heir as the
father or you see the heir as a third party?
Yes, but even that is correct, but even without seeing it as
the father, the question is is does the heir deserve that protection,
because the heir just passively got this windfall, so why should he
necessarily deserve the same protection as somebody who is spending money and
buying something and a third part of it?
Why would it ever occur to him that to do due diligence
for anything?
Yeah exactly, he doesn't have to do due... okay, but that's the
point, why does he deserve protection? Okay, anyway, but that's the issue
by the heir, yes.
So when they say שטר, shtar, this
is
a שטר shtar with עדים? eidim? Correct, שטר shtar with witnesses, yes.
So just a שטר shtar with כתב ידו ksav yado
would not work? Okay, so that's what you're asking.
עדים edim plus, it's a public matter, there's a סופר, sofer, right?
You know, the רשב״ם Rashbam says you gotta get together, do a
whole to-do.
It's abbreviated to, it's very much a שטר shtar meaning to just
basically same thing as an IOU.
An IOU would be like an IOU, exactly like an IOU, correct.
Okay, so what's the
difference? So בקיצור, bekitzur, we've always been brought up to know this
idea that the reason that you have liens by a שטר, shtar,
you don't have liens if there's just witnesses, because a שטר shtar
makes it a public matter, witnesses do not. That's the משנה, mishna,
that's רב ושמואל, Rav and Shmuel, right? רב ושמואל Rav and Shmuel
even go so far to hold this distinction by orphans, by heirs,
let's say. Okay, better word here than orphans, by heirs. But so
why does רב Rav say that when it comes to selling a
piece of land and giving insurance, אחריות achrayus to that sale, and
then liens are created for that insurance if the person has to
go collect, why there does those liens created even just with witnesses?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, the גמרא Gemara says מלווה
אזביני קא רמית? milve azivinei ka ramis? You're trying to challenge, to
make a contradiction between the case of a loan and a case
of a
sale. מלווה? milve? Question mark, exclamation
point. מלווה כי קא יזיף בצינעא קא יזיף. milve ki ka yazif
b'tzina ka yazif. When people borrow money, they borrow in private. Michael
doesn't want to announce to everybody that he needed ten thousand dollars
from me. First of all, it's maybe just סתם stam embarrassing. You
know, people feel like, oh my god, I needed to borrow money,
right? Now maybe you say you do it for commercial purposes, it's
not embarrassing, but besides whether it's embarrassing or not, there's a practical
implication. If everybody knows he needs money and he's cash poor even
if he's asset wealthy, why is there a practical implication? Because taking
advantage of his need for
money, כי היכי דלא לזלו נכסיה עליה. ki heichi d'lo lizlu nichsei
alei. His people, people will lowball him when he tries to sell
his property. They know he took out a million dollar loan from
me, it's coming due, he's selling property. If people know that he's
pressured to raise that money, he's going to, people are going to
lowball him, he's not going to get what he deserves for his
property. So he wants to keep it quiet. So therefore, if it's
done just with witnesses, we'd assume that it is done in a
context in which we're keeping it quiet, okay? I'm making sure there
are witnesses so I can eventually
collect, but I am accommodating Michael that we're keeping it quiet because
I don't want to hurt Michael's financial standing. So therefore, in that
case, a loan with witnesses, you can't, even if you do your
due diligence, you won't be able to find out. That is something
that is really kept quiet and therefore, to protect the purchaser, we
have to say that there are no liens, okay? Because there's no
good way he could find out even if
they will lie,
no, not lie, but you just don't know. Like if people don't
talk about it, how are you going to, I'm about to buy
this plot of land, I'm asking around, does anybody know if there
are liens on the land, does anybody know if, you know, the
guy who owns the land borrowed money? And nobody knows about it,
you know, and the two witnesses who were at the back of
the bar who happen to know about it, they're just keeping quiet,
they're not saying anything. Okay? You know, the borrower cares, meaning the
borrower, no,
the buyer
who's about to buy your land, right, wants to know if there
are any, if you've borrowed money, if there are any liens about
it. Anyway, the point is that nobody has to lie, it's just
that nobody is talking about it and it's being kept quiet and
therefore, the person who we're trying to protect, the person who's buying
the land and needs to know if there are liens or not,
is not in a position to find out that information. And therefore,
we have to protect them and say that there are no liens.
Wait, let's just finish the end of the sentence, then you can
ask all your questions. Okay, מלווה כי קא יזיף כי היכי דלא
לזלו נכסיה עליה. milve ki ka yazif ki heichi d'lo lizlu nichsei
alei. So therefore, if they're just witnesses, it's going to be, the
matter's going to be not public, and not even not public, but
it's going to be kept quiet. Okay, and therefore, in order to
protect the guy who purchases, we have to say there can't be
liens on the land. If there's liens, even if he does his
due diligence, he won't be able to find out about it. That's
the case of borrowing. And therefore, there are only liens if there's
a
שטר. shtar. Okay, אבל מאן דזבין, aval man d'zavin, but let's say
it's the flip. Let's say Michael is selling land, okay? And he's
selling me land and he is providing the insurance, אחריות. achrayus. Okay,
and therefore, I'm going to actually I actually have a lien on
Michael's property when he sells me land. Why? Because if that land
ever gets taken from me, I'm going to collect, get reimbursed from
Michael's property. So he's selling me land with insurance. Okay, and in
that type of a case we say even if there are just
עדים, edim, anybody who wants to buy land from Michael can find
that out. Why can they find out that I have those liens
that were created through insurance? Because Michael is in the process of
selling his land. Okay, so is he going to try to do
that in public or in private? Before he sold it to me,
he's trying to sell his land. He wants to have a bidding
war. He's going to make it a very public matter. I have
these ten acres for sale. Okay? He's going to put up signs,
he's going to, you know, best offer, or whatever it's going to
be, everybody's going to know about it. So the situation that So
the situation that generates the liens on his property is a him
selling property in a very public matter. So therefore, even if there
are just עדים edim and no שטר, shtar, it is something that
is discoverable. And therefore, there are liens that are created just with
עדים. edim. Wait a minute. מאן דזבין, man dezavin, one who
sells, איהו בפרהסיא זבין, ihu befarsya zavin, will do it in public.
יהבו ליה קלא, yehavu lei kala, that it can be a very
public matter. Okay, so bottom line is, there only going to be
liens if the matter is public and now we're even maybe reassessing
what we said before. Maybe it even doesn't even require that much
investigation on behalf of the purchaser. You know, maybe it really is
a public matter. Things with a שטר shtar are public. So if
it's a loan and there's a שטר, shtar, it's public, he can
find out relatively easily. If there are witnesses, because loans are done
in private, then it's not public and maybe it's hard to find
that out. And therefore, a lien only exists with a שטר. shtar.
By a sale, the sale initially would have almost always been done
in as public of a matter as possible. And therefore, says רב,
Rav, even if the liens of the insurance of the sale are
created just through witnesses, it is a public matter and purchasers should
know and therefore there will be liens even just with witnesses. Yes,
Michael and then Eli.
Yeah, I just want to understand. I understand that if there's a
loan I want to keep it private, but the mere presence of
the witness already negates that.
Well, I'm not going to lend you money if I can't have
evidence against you.
I mean, I want to keep it private, but the witnesses, they
couldn't care less about what I want. You know, so like, you
know, we were even talking about how the rumor will get started,
two whatever, you know.
Okay, there's only so much you can do, but the point first
of all is, you know, maybe we're not going to do it,
maybe even when we get the witnesses, like I want to make
sure it's as public of a matter as possible. You want to
make sure it's as private of a matter as possible or whatever
the case might be. You know, but like so maybe the witnesses
will accommodate and try to keep it quiet, but even if not,
we're still going to do it
in a private context. So you're right, it's not completely private, but
it's as private as possible and therefore it's not fair to expose
the purchaser to this thing if it's hard to find out about
it.
I guess Ben Franklin would disagree.
Right, okay, Eli, wait, and then T-David, yes.
Every time somebody sells land, it's they're in danger that there's a,
meaning those liens, how does that work?
What do you mean, the insurance provided by a sale of
land?
If I take a loan from somebody, right, do I have to
list there that I'm putting my נכסים, nechasim, my other
נכסים?
nechasim? No, you, when you borrow money with a שטר, shtar, it
automatically creates liens on your property. You do not have to explicitly
list the property. That's the principle called אחריות טעות סופר. achrayut ta'ut
sofer. Even without mentioning the lien in the document and even without
identifying your property. Obviously we could have a court case because we
could try to be, we could wind up debating whether you purchased
this property before or after I lent you the money, right, but
it's automatic through the שטר. shtar. David?
I was just going to respond to Michael that the lender, based
on what you just outlined, may not want it to be public
either, because if the person has plenty of land and he wants
him to be able to sell it at a full price so
he can get reimbursed.
Oh, that's an interesting point. Oh, that's a nice point. When he
eventually is going to get reimbursed, he actually wants the person to
be in an advantageous position. Unless he's doing predatory lending and using
a cutout to try to buy him back. Exactly. Exactly. The funny
thing of course here you understand is that the money here is
being lent and if we're not using a היתר עסקה, heter iska,
then it's like the lender has like no incentive to be accommodating
and to be
lending. It's only a loss proposition for the lender, right, unless there's
some היתר עסקה heter iska or you know something type of what's
it called about a משכנתא דסורא mashkanta de-Sura and so on, yeah.
So when you just explained to Eli, why is that called אחריות
טעות סופר achrayut ta'ut sofer and not שעבוד טעות סופר? shibud ta'ut
sofer? In other words, it creates a...
The אחריות achrayut and שעבוד shibud are the same.
The lien I thought is the...
Right, but the word אחריות achrayut is meant, it's in this context
means a lien, means a שעבוד. shibud.
Also אחריות achrayut means an insurance to protect...
Right,
right, so it has, אחריות achrayut actually has two meanings. Correct, correct.
To protect the lender and sometimes to protect the borrower.
Well,
the אחריות achrayut is a responsibility which in this context is translated
as the way the responsibility is satisfied is through these liens. But
you're right, it's a non-specific term. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Now that we've figured out that difference between
עדים edim and שטר, shtar, which is a universal distinction in the
גמרא, Gemara, but here was helpful to clarify different contexts, we get
back to a more regular חזקה chazaka thing. אכלה האב שנה והבן
שתים, achlah ha'av shanah ve-haben shtayim, האב שתים והבן שנה. ha'av shtayim
ve-haben shanah. So this goes back to our משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה
Mishnah discussed the issue about the father and the son, right, so
our משנה Mishnah discussed the issue about the... Our משנה Mishnah discussed
two cases, right? One is that a יורש, yoresh, somebody inherited property
and said I've been here three years, you didn't say anything, and
you know, my father had been living there, I can't prove my
father owned it, right? So that was what we discussed the other
day, that you know, that טענינן ליורש, toninu leyoresh, that basically if
you can prove the father was there one day and you've been
here three years, that works. But the other case in the משנה
Mishnah was what was the other case? It was so, your father
sold it to me, you sold it to me, etc. Now let's
say it's a combination of son and father to create the חזקה,
chazakah, and that can work two ways, right? Who was the original
owner of the land, did he die or who was the person
doing the חזקה, chazakah, right, which did he die and his son
continued? So let's take a look. So אכל האב שנה והבן שתים,
achal ha'av shanah ve'haben shtayim, so the father was on the land
for a year and then he died and the בן ben and
the son was there two years, והאב שתים והבן שנה, ve'ha'av shtayim
ve'haben shanah, or the father two years and the son one year,
or even more extreme case, האב שנה והבן שנה והלוקח שנה. ha'av
shanah ve'haben shanah ve'halokeach shanah. Okay, ראובן, Reuven, what would be the
case? יעקב Yaakov was there for a year, he died, he saw,
you know, יוסף Yosef was there for another year and then יוסף
Yosef sold it to, I don't know, מרדכי. Mordechai. Okay, so these,
now so is that considered, we discussed שלשה לקוחות shlosha lekuchos that
the original owner will he, will know about the idea of שלשה
לקוחות shlosha lekuchos through a שטר shtar and he'll see that as
continuous, through שטרות shtarot and he'll see that as continuous. So here,
right, that would be a similar question, from, from you know, יוסף
Yosef to מרדכי Mordechai if there's a שטר shtar that connects them.
How about from יעקב Yaakov dying to יוסף Yosef inheriting it, okay,
will that also be something that we'll assume that the original owner
will hear the son is on the land that the father was
on and that he should therefore see it, perceive it as a
continuous חזקה? chazakah? So the הלכה halacha is let's see what the
answer is. Okay, let me read the line and then we'll clarify
it. הרי זו חזקה, harei zu chazakah, that works. Okay, now what
do you want to clarify? Yes.
I wanted to know how he knew the two witnesses were in
the bar. No, never mind. The
original owner is, by the original owner you mean the מערער, me'arer,
someone who's coming to לערער. le'arer. Yeah. Yeah. That's all.
No, but he clearly is the original owner. He only has a
position to be מערער me'arer because he's the original owner of the
land. That's established. Now, all right, now, it's interesting like what if
the original owner comes and claims like I didn't know this guy
was his son, what I'm supposed to know the relations, the you
know, the relatives of all the people that buy land from me,
right? Or let's say this was some person who was a son
that was born in some foreign land to another wife who's you
know, who nobody in the town even knew about. Like one has
to imagine that there might be different circumstances where this doesn't work
if there's a legitimate claim that you had no idea that this
guy was the son. But anyway, but presuming we're dealing with something
that everybody knows everybody's business and it's a small town or whatever,
then you understand why this
works. Okay, now, הרי זו חזקה, harei zu chazakah, למימרא leimara says
גמרא Gemara דלוקח אית ליה קלא. delokeach is lei kala. Now we're
revisiting what we just said a minute ago. Okay, sometimes the גמרא
Gemara does that. You're saying, we understand a father and a son
people understand that it's the son and therefore that it's a continuation,
but how do you know that this guy who purchased it, it's
a continuation and the original owner knew that it was sold to
him? Maybe he's just some random person. Okay, the, now again we
said that a minute ago because of the שטר, shtar, but let's
take a look. רמינהי, remini, I'll ask on this, אכלה בפני האב
שנה ובפני הבן שנה, achla bifnei ha'av shanah u'bifnei haben shanah, this
is the
reverse.
The guy did a חזקה chazakah and the original owner who was
alive for a year and then he died, and then his son,
the חזקה chazakah continued two years into the son's life, or בפני
האב שתים ובפני הבן שנה, bifnei ha'av shtayim u'bifnei haben shanah, or
the reverse, right, the father was alive for two years and then
he died and then the son, this is the original owner now
died, or בפני האב שנה ובפני הבן שנה ובפני הלוקח שנה, bifnei
ha'av shanah u'bifnei haben shanah u'bifnei halokeach shanah, the father you know
lived for a year died, the son was there for a year
and then the son sold it to a third party, okay, and
while all that time you're on the land. Now the question of
course you should ask is if you remember a previous גמרא, Gemara,
the sale of the son to a third party should function as
a חזקה. chazakah. You are asserting, the original owner's asserting their ownership
rights. What?
As a מחאה. mecha.
I said, sorry, thank you, as a מחאה. mecha. The original owner
is, is asserting their, their ownership rights. Okay, so we'll see about
that in a minute but let's hold that for now. That's actually
essentially going to be our question. Okay, ובפני שנה ובפני הבן שנה
ובפני הבן שנה ובפני הלוקח שנה, u'bifnei shanah u'bifnei haben shanah u'bifnei
haben shanah u'bifnei halokeach shanah, הרי זו חזקה, harei zu chazakah, that
works. Okay, now by the way that itself is a חידוש chiddush
before you even get to the לוקח lokeach because you could say
you know, how do we assume that the son can immediately come
up to speed with his father's business dealings and know the land,
you know, and know all of the properties and and you know
and get a chance to look into it and see that somebody
is you know has this adverse possession of a property in order
to do a חזקה. chazakah. Okay, I mean the son is a
גדול, gadol, we're not talking about a minor, but nevertheless there's definitely
a big חידוש chiddush in this if you ask me. But the
גמרא'ס Gemara's question is why does it work for the לוקח? lokeach?
The sale to the לוקח lokeach should be a מחאה, mecha, and
the only logic that it doesn't function as a מחאה mecha is
that we will say that when you sell something people don't find
out. It doesn't have a קול. kol. So if it doesn't, it
doesn't serve as a מחאה mecha'ah because the מחזיק machzik doesn't find
out. Then when the מחזיק machzik sells it, and the third guy
does it for a year, it shouldn't serve as a חזקה, chazakah,
because the original owner doesn't find out. You got it? So this
is the question. If a sale takes place, do we assume the
opposing side will find out? So if a sale to a לוקח
lokeach isn't a מחאה, mecha'ah, it must be only because we assume
the opposing side doesn't find out. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי
סלקא דעתך לוקח אית ליה קלא, ve'isalka daitach lokeach it lei kala,
if you think a לוקח lokeach has a קול, kol, אין לך
מחאה גדולה מזו, ein lach mecha'ah gedolah mizo, there's no greater מחאה
mecha'ah than selling it to somebody else and asserting your ownership. So
must be there's no קול, kol, and therefore how do you reconcile
this? Here we see that selling it is not found, does not
have a קול, kol, and you're saying that to create a continuity
of חזקה chazakah it does have a קול. kol. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר רב פפא כי תניא ההיא במוכר שדותיו סתם. amar
Rav Pappa, ki tanya hi bemocher sadosav stam. No, no, no. That
case is where the father, the original owner, died, and then his
son has it, and then the son sells it to someone else.
When the son sold it to this third party, he didn't say,
I am selling you that plot of land at the corner of,
whatever, 239th and Independence. Okay, he said to you, I am selling
you all of my father's land, all the plants that are, you
know, it's all of the property. So all of the property isn't
a מחאה, mecha'ah, because I here who bought the land from the
father am saying, that doesn't include my land, that's no longer the
father's property. So without it being specifically identified, it's not a מחאה,
mecha'ah, because from my perspective, right, that land is no longer, is
not included in the umbrella, all of my father's land, right? Because
it's no longer the father's land. Okay, but if it's identified, then
it is a מחאה. mecha'ah. Now of course תוספות Tosafos points out
that an easier distinction would have been whether it was sold with
a שטר shtar or was it sold with עדים, edim, okay, which
we're still maintaining that. So if you there is a sale that
is done with a שטר, shtar, then we assume the other side
finds out. If I sell it, then it works to create a
continuity of a חזקה, chazakah, and the other side will assume the
other side finds out. If the original owner sells it with a
שטר, shtar, it functions as a מחאה, mecha'ah, and therefore I will
find out. If that was done with עדים, edim, it doesn't function
as a, there's no קול, kol, it's not חזקה. chazakah. If he
does a sale with עדים edim and not a שטר, shtar, it's
no קול, kol, it's not a מחאה. mecha'ah. Even if it's done
with a שטר, shtar, what we're saying here is it's not a
מחאה mecha'ah if the שטר shtar does not specifically identify this plot
of land. If all the שטר shtar says is, I'm selling all
the land, then that's not a מחאה, mecha'ah, because that doesn't include
from my perspective this plot of land.
Yeah, some people are fuzzy about the facts of this, of this
תשב''ח Tashbach case. What I mean, who what's the force of בפני
האב? bifnei ha'av?
בפני האב bifnei ha'av means that it's not that the, it's just
a way of designating the father-son sale as the, from as the
original owners. Not as if it's אכלה האב, achla ha'av, that's the
person that's מחזיק machzik it, then his son eats it, and then
whatever. מחזיק. machzik. If it's אכלה בפני האב, achla bifnei ha'av, then
the issue of אב av and בן ben is the original owner.
I am eating it in their presence. They are the original owner.
I am being מחזיק machzik it in their presence. So the בפני
bifnei switches to whether we're talking about the מחזיק machzik son or
the original owner. Okay, so that's very interesting. But again, I find
the idea that it works בפני הבן, bifnei haben, you know, a
real חידוש, chiddush, because it requires the son to say to, you
know, get up to speed very quickly in the father's estate, in
the father's dealings. Okay, now we move on to the next משנה.
mishnah. And this next משנה mishnah is going to continue to deal
with obviously חזקה chazakah three years, and which types of things would
not constitute a חזקה chazakah based on the person's general relationship to
the land,
but
also along the way deal with other forms of חזקה chazakah as
well. So let's take a look. Both the חזקה chazakah that creates
a presumption of ownership and a חזקה chazakah that actually effectuates ownership.
So, האומנין. ha'umnim. An אומן uman is a craftsman. Okay, and basically
a, so let's say, let's say I am in the business of
doing, I'm a dry cleaner. Okay, or I am a shoemaker and
I do shoe repairs. And basically you gave off, you know, I
have in my possession
David's nice, you know, beautiful Armani suit. And I say, oh yeah,
this is mine, even though we all knew, even though we all
knew that David owned it beforehand. Why? חזקה מה שתחת יד אדם
הרי הוא שלו. chazakah mah shetachas yad adam harei hu shelo. We
have a presumption when we're dealing with מטלטלין metaltelin and not קרקע,
karka, that anything in my possession, a presumption that it's mine. So
what do you think? No, excuse me. No. Not something that people
give to you to repair because that's your profession. Okay, that you
don't have a חזקה. chazakah. I have a store which is, which
is, we fix broke, cracked iPhone screens. And then I say, oh,
all these iPhones, they're all mine. I'm in possession of them, right?
No, no, no. That doesn't work, okay. Even if we don't know
that David gave me his suit, we didn't witness David giving me
his suit and dropping it off at my dry. Dropping it off
at my dry cleaner store, okay, I just, I just start wearing
David's suit, right, that is not a presumption of ownership because that's
his business, that's my business. Okay, so אומנים umnim don't have a
חזקה. chazakah.
Now that is
not a חזקה chazakah of three years, that is a חזקה chazakah
of מטלטלין metaltelin of chattel, which is a חזקה chazakah immediately. Any
possession of moveables, of chattel, it's presumed to be direct possession, it's
presumed to be mine, but it's not true if we're dealing with
objects of the types of things that I'm actually, you know, that
I'm in the trade of, of, you know, of handling and of
dealing with and so on.
Now there's the flip side, I mean, meaning anyone then can go
and say, oh it's mine, it's mine, it's mine.
No, no, you have to prove that you were the original owner.
Okay, if you prove you're the original owner, then my simple possession
of it is not sufficient. So if I actually offered to buy
it from you and I do, I better get some witnesses or
something because I won't be believed. Okay, but that's an אומן uman
does not have חזקה. chazakah. Now there's a broader category, which is
that if it's things that are normally rented or lent, which is
from the perspective of the owner, not of the receiver. Okay, if
I basically normally lend out my lawnmower to my
neighbors, okay, even if I'm not renting it and making a profit,
and certainly if I rent out my cars, you know, and I'm
a Hertz Rental Car place or whatever, so your possession of my
lawnmower or of my car is not considered, is not presumed ownership.
Okay, so it's the same type of an idea. Okay, so אומנים
umnim don't have חזקה. chazakah.
Or naturally, why would they have to say it about a קרקע?
karka?
Well, the גמרא gemara is going to say that it's relatively obvious,
okay, I don't know what to say. Sometimes we say obvious things.
Okay, so that is a חזקה chazakah not of three years, that's
a חזקה chazakah of immediate profession, of possession, and as we're going
to see in the גמרא, gemara, some did not even have this
word in the משנה, mishnah, A because it's relatively obvious and B
because it's not your חזקות chazakot we've been talking about. We've been
talking about three years חזקה. chazakah. So now the משנה mishnah shifts
to the חזקה chazakah of
קרקע. karka. והשותפין, vehashutfin, partners. Okay, so Chanan and I are partners
in this field, and he's been working the field for three years,
even though we're partners, and then he says, oh yeah, I've been
working it because Dov sold it to me three years ago and
I don't have the שטר. shtar. It's like, no, like maybe that's
possible, but if you're a partner there's a giant reasonable you know
likelihood that you have some arrangement that you're going to work it
for three years and Dov maybe pays you for it or maybe
he's not partners with you at all.
What? It's known that we're partners, okay, or you know, it was
known that we were partners and then he claims I sold it
to him. So we say no, your חזקה chazakah doesn't mean it,
there's a reasonable likelihood that you have some arrangement going on and
you're here not because you bought, you know, you're working the whole
land and you're not splitting it for other reasons than purchase. So
that's שותפין. shutfin. והאריסין, vehaarisin, okay, or let's say it was well
known that you know that Chanan was my sharecropper. And then he's
on it for three years. Now, of course if he's stom on
it and he's giving me 50 or 20 percent or whatever percentage
of the wheat, there's not even a possibility of a חזקה. chazakah.
Then it's evidence that he's a sharecropper. But no, it went for
three years and he was harvesting the whole thing and depositing it
all in his own bank account. Nevertheless, we still say that there's
you know that we're going to not assume that means he owned
it. Maybe he pre-sold all the stuff deposited and then he paid
me a check, you know, at some later time, right? Maybe you
know we're going to arrange it that he's going to get the
first three years all to himself and I'm going to get the
next three years all to myself. So there's you know the context
that we know makes us presume that it does not demonstrate
ownership. והאריסין והאפיטרופין, vehaarisin vehaapotropin, which is that Chanan is the you
know is the what do you call it?
He's a caretaker,
I think that's a good word, for the for like orphans let's
say or whatever, and then he's working the land, so like of
course we're not going to assume that he owns it, he's there
in his role as caretaker. Okay, אפיטרופוס apotropos is more than caretaker.
Caretaker is executor. Caretaker is somebody you hire. אפיטרופוס apotropos is somebody
who sort of has like power of
attorney. Executor, trustee, trustee, okay, administrator. אין להם חזקה. ein lahem chazakah.
They have no חזקה. chazakah. Right? Yosef would not have חזקה chazakah
on the property of Potiphar's
household. Okay. לא לאיש חזקה בנכסי אשתו. lo le'ish chazakah benichsei ishto.
This is like so
obvious. A man gets married, his wife's property, that's the נכסי מלוג,
nichsei melog, that he retains title to, the husband gets all of
the produce from that property during the marriage. So of course the
husband's going to be working the land and reaping the produce. So
it's obviously in the context to the fact that he has right
to the פירות peirot and that's why he's working, not because he
actually owns title to it. So that's like
obvious. ולא לאשה חזקה בנכסי בעלה. velo le'ishah chazakah benichsei baalah. But
let's say the opposite, let's say I own all these orchards, I
get married, and my wife goes ahead and she takes over administrating
all of the orchards and working it and whatever and showing herself
as a בעלת הבית. baalat habayis. Nevertheless, we say, no, you know
what? Like maybe she's doing it because we're married and not because
she's actually the owner. I mean, the רשב"ם Rashbam also throws in
the fact that she also is entitled to מזונות, mezonos, you know,
I have to provide for her, so you know, it could be
that she's working the, you know, working the land or whatever to
ensure that she gets provided from from
the land. Okay now, ולא אב בנכסי הבן ולא הבן בנכסי האב.
Velo av b'nichsei haben velo haben b'nichsei ha'av. Similarly father working the
son's land, son working the father's land, we all assume that they're
doing it as some type of a context of a familial relationship
and not because of one of them, you know, the other person,
one of them bought it from the other. So if you actually
did buy it, you need to watch onto your שטר, shtar, okay,
in those
cases. במה דברים אמורים? Bameh devarim amurim? When is this true? במחזיק.
B'machzik. That is all about a case of חזקה, chazakah, meaning a
חזקה chazakah that is coming to demonstrate
ownership. אבל בנותן מתנה, Aval benotein matanah, now we are shifting to
a completely different concept of חזקה chazakah which is the act, a
single concrete act that effects a change of ownership. Right when you
buy קרקע, karka, how do you transfer
ownership? כסף שטר וחזקה. Kesef shtar v'chazakah. Either by the giving of
the money or by the writing of a document and the handing
over the document becomes the instrument to change ownership, or by doing
an act of that demonstrating possession, a single specific act. So that's
a different, so there's three types of חזקה chazakah mentioned in the
משנה. Mishnah. The immediate possession of מטלטלין, metaltelin, which is a presumption
of ownership, three years' possession of land, which is a presumption of
ownership, and a specific concrete act done to land, which is an
act that effects change, effects, you know, change of ownership. So that's
what it says. אבל, Aval, so there's no question of what's going
on. We all know I'm trying to sell it to you, what
act creates that change? אבל במחזיק אבל בנותן מתנה, Aval b'machzik aval
benotein matanah,
I'm giving you a gift. ואחים שחלקו, V'achim shechalku, or let's say
I am dividing it with my brother, we inherited an estate and
we're dividing it between so each of us has to take possession
on our half. Okay, that's a type of a taking of possession,
a splitting, but it's through each one takes possession of their half.
והמחזיק בנכסי הגר. V'hamachzik b'nichsei hageir.
Let's say a somebody who had converted died without any children, so
since they don't have any, you know, I mean any other relatives,
so that property is considered becomes ownerless. So in all those
cases, נעל גדר ופרץ, na'al geder ufaratz, if you either נעל וגדר
ופרץ, na'al v'geder ufaratz, if you did some type of a thing
to improve the land. And here by the way is a basic
difference between the חזקה chazakah of demonstrating ownership and a חזקה chazakah
of taking possession. A חזקה chazakah of demonstrating ownership is basically through
you benefiting from the land. Meaning if I just plow, I mean
although this was discussed earlier in the גמרא, Gemara, it was debated,
if I just plow and I turn over the soil is that
a חזקה chazakah or not? But the general, the general, you know,
inclination was to say it wasn't because the original owner can say,
you're just benefiting the land, why should I say anything? It's only
when you when you gain benefit from the land, you harvest the
crops, that then that's a חזקה. chazakah. So a חזקה chazakah of
demonstrating ownership is that you're deriving benefit from the land. A classic
חזקה chazakah of taking possession is that you actually also are doing
something to improve the land. All right, which one could ask like
why that flip, but you know, but but maybe because as soon
as you take possession your immediate, you know, like I don't know,
like why should it be that like when I take you know,
there's different reasons I could benefit the land because you paid me
to, I could benefit it because I'm an owner. I could derive
benefit from the land because I'm an owner, I could derive benefit
from the land because, I don't know, I'm a sharecropper or something.
So it's not exactly clear to me why that's, there's, but I
do know why the מחזיק machzik that demonstrates ownership has to be
deriving benefit for the reason I said that only that provides sufficient
provocation for the original owner. It's not clear to me why the
חזקה chazakah of taking possession is fundamentally one of giving benefit to
the land. I'll take it in a minute but let's at least
read that. So נעל na'al is I lock the gate, okay, I
protect it from being, you know, from animals coming and eating the
weeds or whatever. וגדר v'geder is I actually build a fence or
or a wall. ופרץ u'faratz is I make an opening in the
wall but not in a destructive way, in a way that actually
it's like I'm fixing it, I'm creating like a necessary opening in
the gate or something like that. כל שהוא, kol shehu, even in
a small portion of the land, הרי זו חזקה, harei zu chazakah,
that is the act of חזקה chazakah of a different type of
a חזקה, chazakah, an act of taking possession, which again is something
done more through the giving of benefit to the land rather than
the taking of benefit from the land. Yes Bob.
What what is this situation that you described and the land is
unoccupied, let's say a person owns the land, the person has no
living relatives, the person dies, who then takes?
We find
any person who is a naturally-born Jew has some living relative, some
other Jew is related to them going all the way back to
אברהם אבינו, Avraham Avinu, we just have to find it. Like what
happens if we've researched and researched and researched and we have no
idea and like no known relative? Ancestry.com.
I
don't know that's a good question. I mean maybe we treat it
as הפקר, hefker, but if somebody can eventually come and prove that
they were related, you know, then we would have to take it
away from the person who took possession and Give it to that
person. But I don't know what we would do in the interim.
It's a good question. Yeah. Yeah. Okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
So the משנה mishna. *Mishnah*. So the first part, ובין שני רחוקים
*u'vein shnei rechokim* and אומנין, שותפין, אריסין, ואפוטרופסין *umnin, shutfin, arisin, ve'apotropsin*.
Right.
That's on קרקע *karka*. Only the first word אומנין *umnin* is not
קרקע *karka*. And the whole first until the...
I know the first is not...
because אומנין *umnin* is not a word by קרקע *karka*. By קרקע
*karka* it's אריס, חכיר, קבלן *aris, chakir, kablan*. אומנין *umnin* never applies
to the קרקע *karka*.
Because אומנין *umnin* is on מטלטלין *metaltelin*
and the others are on קרקע *karka*. And then לא לאיש חזקה
chazakah
ולא לאשה *lo le'ish chazaka ve'lo le'isha*...
that's also קרקע *karka*. Everything is קרקע *karka* except for the first
word אומנין *umnin*, but the shift in the second part of the
משנה mishna. *Mishnah* about the מדברים במי שמחזיק *me'devarim be'mi she'machzik* as
a demonstration of ownership and a חזקה chazakah *chazaka* of a taking
of possession.
Yeah, but I'm trying to understand what the אין להם חזקה chazakah.
*ein lahem chazaka* is doing before לא לאיש חזקה chazakah, *lo le'ish
chazaka*.
Oh, yeah, I don't know why it splits that way. Probably because
one is just a simple list. It's probably because as an oral
tradition, אומנין, שותפין, אריסין, ואפוטרופסין *umnin, shutfin, arisin, ve'apotropsin* are all just
individual words that name people's status. And then the rest are actual
specific relationships. איש באשתו *ish be'ishto*, you know, אב ובן *av u'ven*,
בן ואב *ben ve'av*. They're clustered differently. Yeah.
What all these mean is man, wife... when a man gets married,
a man takes possession of the wife's property. The man and woman
get divorced.
Yes, the wife reclaims her property. Yes, yes, yes. Okay, let's take
a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. אבוה דשמואל ולוי *Avuha de'Shmuel
ve'Levi*, who were contemporaries, שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel's* father and לוי *Levi*, תנו
שותף shutaf אין לו חזקה chazakah *tanu shutaf ein lo chazaka*, וכל
שכן אומן *ve'kol sheken uman*. They don't have the word אומן *uman*
in the משנה mishna. *Mishnah*. It just says a שותף shutaf *shutaf*
doesn't have חזקה chazakah *chazaka*, and certainly an אומן *uman* as all
that you said. An אומן *uman*, that's the guy, the dry cleaner,
doesn't have חזקה chazakah *chazaka* on clothes is like obvious. Okay? People
give him those clothes, whatever. This is clear. Whereas a שותף shutaf
*shutaf*, it's not as obvious. If חנן Chanan *Chanan* is working the
whole land, even though we're partners, well, why aren't I not working,
why am I not contributing my half? So we could actually question
whether a שותף shutaf *shutaf* has חזקה chazakah *chazaka* or not.
But maybe our partnership was used to provide the money.
I understand, but it's not as obvious as אומן *uman*. אומן *uman*,
there's no question should not have a חזקה chazakah. *chazaka*. So therefore
they say שותף shutaf *shutaf* and you don't even have to say
אומן *uman*. שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*, however, שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* disagrees with his
father. תני אומן אין לו חזקה chazakah, *tani uman ein lo chazaka*.
No, no, no, only an אומן *uman* doesn't have חזקה chazakah *chazaka*
because obviously we know that דב *Dov* has suits for different... for
other reasons and he'll have the whole suit. אבל שותף shutaf יש
לו חזקה yesh lo chazakah? *aval shutaf yesh lo chazaka*. So the
real point here though is שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* takes out the word
שותף shutaf, *shutaf* from the משנה mishna *Mishnah* and he actually says
that if חנן Chanan *Chanan* there is working the whole land, he
actually does have חזקה chazakah. *chazaka* because he is taking... he is
actually on that land that I should have been working at least,
you know, partially. And the fact that he is the sole person
to work it for three years shows he bought it from me.
But all he has to do is show up for one day,
right? That's sufficient. What? What? All he has to do is show
up
for work for one day. Exactly. Exactly. If I show up for
one day, I protest for one day, exactly. Okay, ואזל שמואל Shmuel's
לטעמיה *ve'azal Shmuel le'ta'ameih*. So now we're going to focus not on
the language of the משנה *Mishnah* but on שמואל'ס *Shmuel's* basically, you
know, position that a שותף shutaf *shutaf* has a חזקה chazakah. *chazaka*
against our text of the משנה *Mishnah*. ואזל שמואל לטעמיה *ve'azal Shmuel
le'ta'ameih*. He goes according to his reasoning. דאמר שמואל השותפין מחזיקין זה
על זה *de'amar Shmuel ha'shutfin machzikin zeh al zeh*. שותפין *shutfin* actually
can have a חזקה chazakah. *chazaka* against one another. ומעידין זה על
זה *u'me'idin zeh al zeh*. They can testify on behalf of one
another. Now that sounds crazy because testifying on behalf of your partner,
you're obviously נוגע בעדות *nogei'a be'edut*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going
to deal with that. That'll be tomorrow's דף *daf*. Okay? ונעשים שומרי
שכר זה לזה *ve'na'asim shomrei sachar zeh la'zeh*. Now also they are
שומר שכר *shomer sachar*. Let's say for example, what let's say for
example,
we...
you know, חנן Chanan *Chanan* and I here are שותפין *shutfin* in
this boat, okay, so that we rent out, you know, for business.
And I'm saying, you know, חנן *Chanan*, you go ahead and... you
know, today's your day, you watch the boat, I have to go
take care of some personal business. And the boat goes ahead and
gets broken or gets stolen, okay? Now what happens? Do we each
suffer the loss, or do I say, hey חנן *Chanan*, that was
your day of watching, you were a שומר *shomer* on my half.
So because it got stolen and you are שומר שכר *shomer sachar*,
we'll get to the where's the שכר *sachar* in a minute, it's
all your loss. You have to recompense me because it got stolen
under your watch, even though it was both of our boats. Now,
why is he a שומר שכר *shomer sachar*? So the שכר *sachar*
is that because we trade off days watching the boat, or he
watches it on my day off and I watch it on his
day off, so he's getting paid to watch it in exchange for
the fact that I'll watch it for him on his day off.
So that is considered to be a שכר *sachar* and you're considered
to be... so we consider... so that's a big נפקא מינה *nafka
mina*, right? It means when you're the one watching it, it's all
going to be on you if something goes wrong. But why shouldn't
it be proportional?
Why... What? What? I would have thought it would be proportional because
he's watching it... you're the total owner, as it were.
No, no, no. No, he's the total owner on his half and
I'm the half... no, I'm half owner, on half owner.
For your half?
He compensated for my half.
For your half. Right. Oh, compensated for my...
for my half. But if he wasn't a שומר שכר *shomer sachar*,
I would... we would both lose the boat. It would be both
of our loss. Now I get half of it back, I get
my half compensated.
Oh, the whole half,
you mean?
The whole half compensated for. But if it was an you know
the whole
half of the
half. Right. My whole ownership of it, yeah.
I didn't understand how they can be עדים edim? for each other.
Wouldn't they have to be? Yes of course that's the
point.
How can they be עדים?
Alright, we're going to see that. Okay, now, so we're going to
unpack this whole statement. Okay, everybody calm down. Now, okay, now, רמי
ליה רב אבא לרב יהודה בר מרסתא דבי רב. Rami lei Rabbi
Abba le-Rav Yehuda bar Marastha de-bei Rav. So רמי... Rami... so רב
אבא Rabbi Abba sort of challenged this statement of שמואל that a
שותף shutaf has a חזקה chazakah, במערתא be-ma'aratha in the cave of
the house of רב. Rav. I don't know what במערתא be-ma'aratha means.
The mansion? No, it means like maybe, you know, רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, they all decided to hold their ישיבה
yeshiva in a cave or something, I really don't know what במערתא
be-ma'aratha means. Okay, some have the גירסא girsa of במעצרתא, be-matzarta, which
basically means in the pressing floor, which probably makes more sense that
they had their ישיבה, yeshiva, you know, in this big room which
wasn't used for part of the year, right, this place where they
would, you know, do where they would press the olives or whatever
they would do. Anyway, okay, so this is where they had their
ישיבה. yeshiva. Okay, so here's the contradiction. דבי רב זכאי, de-bei Rav
Zakkai, excuse me, house of רב זכאי, Rav Zakkai, or the ישיבה
yeshiva of רב זכאי. Rav Zakkai. מי אמר שמואל שותף יש לו
חזקה? Mi amar Shmuel shutaf yesh lo chazakah? Did שמואל really say
that a שותף can have a חזקה chazakah. on the other half?
ואמר שמואל שותף כיורד ברשות דמי. Ve-amar Shmuel shutaf ke-yored birshut dami.
When a שותף is working in the other half of the field,
you know, now again, it's not exactly like we have a line
drawn in the middle of the field, but you know, he's sort
of working the whole property and even if he's working it without
explicit permission from me, it's as though I am giving him permission.
Anytime he works the property, even if he's working the whole property
and even if he hasn't taken permission from me, it's like he
has permission. So what we assume that means is that we don't
look at it as, as חנן provided us the nice phrase before,
adverse possession. Since a שותף is always considered to have permission to,
you know, a certain amount of autonomy and license even without asking
permission
from his fellow partner, so he's never adversely possessing. So presumably that
means a שותף doesn't have חזקה. chazakah. Okay, so the גמרא
says יש לו חזקה? chazakah. ואמר שמואל שותף כיורד ברשות דמי. Ve-amar
Shmuel shutaf ke-yored birshut dami. לאו למימר דשותף אין לו חזקה? lav
le-meimar de-shutaf ein lo chazakah? Doesn't that imply that there's no חזקה,
chazakah. it's never seen as adverse possession? I always, you know, I
let him do that and maybe again there's always an implication I'll
do my part, he's doing his part. Anyway, לא קשיא. lo kashya.
הא דנחית לכולא הא דנחית לפלגא. ha de-nachis le-kula ha de-nachis le-palga.
No, it's not a problem. The issue is what does it mean,
how is he taking possession? Is it on all of it or
is it on half of it? Now, first of all, what does
it mean to be doing חזקה chazakah, on half? If he's only
doing חזקה chazakah. on half, like we each get half, what's the
issue? So the point is, there's a better half and a worse
half. Okay, I mean let's say they're worth equal amounts, okay, but
even though they might be worth equal amounts, but everybody would rather
have the part that is, you know, more fertile land even if
it's less acreage than the more acreage less fertile land, okay. So
and חנן basically has been working the better half for three years
without any protest from me. And his claim is not that he
bought the whole land from me, his claim is we split it
and this is my half. And the proof is that I worked
this half for three years without any protest. That's the case of
לפלגא. le-palga.
לכולא le-kula and I'm not giving you any of the produce, right,
and you're keeping all the produce from that half. The לכולא le-kula
is that חנן is working the whole land and saying that he
bought the whole thing from me, he bought my half. Okay, so
what we're saying is, for one of those a חזקה will work
and for one of those a חזקה against me won't work. Now,
which is better and which is worse? So the גמרא says, the
גמרא says like this: אמרי לה להאי גיסא ואמרי לה להאי גיסא.
amri lei le-hai gisa ve-amri lei le-hai gisa. Some say it one
way and some say it the other way. So now we can
try to figure out which logic makes sense. So if he's working
his half for three straight years, okay, we could say that actually
works against me because
here
he is, I'm present, I am not taking the three years off,
you know, to go lounge around in Hawaii, okay. I am here
on the land working my half and he's working his half. So
if I am present, then I shouldn't let him use it for
three years straight. We should have done some rotation. So in that
case that I was present and he was doing three years on
his half, that would be a good חזקה. But if he did
the whole thing for three years, that's not a חזקה, you know
why I didn't do anything? Because I wanted to take three years
off and go to Hawaii and the next three years I'll do
it, you do it for three years I'll do it for three
years.
So the thing about the half and the half?
No, because then I'm present, I'm working my half.
That's exactly why he has a חזקה because you're there.
No, no, no, but that maybe I we split it. So the...
That's one approach. One approach is that if I'm here, then I
shouldn't let him work there for three years straight if he doesn't
really own it. We should, we would normally switch off. But if
I'm not around and he's doing the whole thing, then you don't
assume switch off, maybe you take it for a while, then I'll
take it for a while. That's that way. The other way you
could say no, the opposite, which is, is that as long as
he's working half and I'm working half, we're making it clear that
I'm still a part owner of this field, right? And the fact
that you're not, you're only, you know, so, I should worry which
half are you working and so on? Like, no, that's not a
חזקה. But to actually let you use the whole field for three
years, you know, uninterrupted, the part that's even mine, or whatever, the
whole field, demonstrate you're acting as an owner of the whole field,
that is something I should be מוחה mocheh for. So some say
it one way, some say it the other way. Right, yeah, could
work either way, it could work both, you could split it and
then you don't know which way to split it. But the bottom
line is that at least שמואל says there are some cases in
which a שותף does have חזקה. That even though you're a שותף,
we would say that the owner, it is, you know, should have
protested, and by not protesting, you have a חזקה.
Disagreeing with our משנה.
Disagreeing with our משנה. The text of our משנה. Okay. רבינא אמר,
Ravina amar, now רבינא Ravina says, הא דנחית
לכולה. ha d'nhis l'kulah. No, no, no, there are two scenarios that
Chanan is using the whole field, one he has a חזקה, one
he doesn't have a חזקה. What's the difference? לא קשיא. lo kashya.
הא דאית בה דין חלוקה, ha d'it bei din chaluka, הא דלית
בה דין חלוקה. ha d'leit bei din chaluka. Is the field big
enough to split between the two of us? Okay.
Back to the beginning of the מסכת.
masechet. Exactly. If it was a very small plot of land that
we can't actually, no side can force a split, because there's not
sufficient land for any one person, okay, in that type of a
case, alright, then we would say that, now I have to remember
which way this goes. If it's לית בה דין חלוקה, leit bei
din chaluka, it's not a חזקה. Oh yeah, because since it's such
a small plot of land, right, it doesn't make sense for us
to be working it together. Okay, it's such a small plot, you
understand, like one person, you know, will work on it at a
time and maybe Chanan works for a few years and I'll work
for a few years, okay, although you could still say why don't
we alternate years. But anyway, if it's a small plot, it makes
no sense for us to be working together, so in that type
of a case, it's not a חזקה. But if it's a bigger
plot that it's possible to split, then it also means it might
make sense for us to join in the effort. And if I'm
not joining in the effort and he's the only one working it,
then it is a, for three years, then it would be a
חזקה. So the bottom line is although the משנה says a שותף
does not have חזקה, שמואל says there are some circumstances where he
does. If he's working half, if he's working the whole thing, if
it has דין חלוקה, din chaluka, doesn't, there's some circumstances where we
would assume that I should, it's not a categorical exclusion, and there
are cases where I should be provoked and my silence actually would
allow a חזקה. Okay, so we will now tomorrow go to the
cases, no, because it's too complicated. So tomorrow we're going to continue
to unpack שמואל case. Okay, let's pick up tomorrow where
this one שותף doesn't.